Berman, Frederic S.; Papers apap229
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Frederic S. Berman Papers
1962-1975
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Berman, Frederic S.
apap229
2.0 cubic ft.
The Frederic S. Berman Papers predominantly document his service in the New York State Senate through correspondence, newsclippings, bills, research material and campaign literature. In addition, there are files pertaining to his post-Senatorial career as the Commissioner of the New York City Rent and Housing Department and as a New York City Criminal Court Judge.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Frederic Berman initially donated his papers to Syracuse University in a series of accessions beginning in 1966. In 2006, the papers were transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical Sketch
Frederic S. Berman was born on March 7, 1927, in New York to his parents Abraham and Rose (Baum) Berman. His father was a lawyer. He graduated from Columbia College in 1949 and received his law degree from New York Law School in 1951. Berman practiced as an attorney at the firm Berman & Berman from 1952-1964 and again from 1969-1972, specializing in business law. He also was an adjunct member of the faculty at New York Law School from 1958-2003, teaching such courses as criminal law, personal property, municipal law, and post-conviction remedies and procedures.
Berman entered public service in the 1960s. Voters from the 20th District elected him to the New York State Senate in 1964. A Democrat, he served from 1964-1966 and focused on issues of air pollution, tenants' rights, and legislative ethics. He was a member of the Corporations, Education, Finance, Motor Vehicles and Transportation and Taxation Committees. As the Commissioner of the New York City Rent and Housing Department from 1966-1969 he spearheaded efforts to slow rising rent through rent control and reform measures. He also served as a New York City Criminal Court Judge from 1973-1976 and sat on the New York State Supreme Court from 1976-1997.
Beginning in 2006, he served as adjunct professor emeritus at New York Law School and was known as an authority on law and social change.
In January 2020, Berman passed away in a nursing home at 92. He was survived by his second wife, Barbra Cohn, and children, Anthony and James Berman, from his first marriage.
Scope and Contents
The collection predominantly contains materials acquired by Frederic Berman during his time as a New York State Senator. Series 1, Senatorial Papers, contains campaign information as well as results from public opinion surveys. Campaign literature from Bruno Cappellini, Eleanor Clark French, John G. Heimann, Eric M. Javits, Robert Kennedy, and John V. Lindsay, and other contemporary New York politicians is found throughout the files. The Berman Papers also feature a substantial variety of newsclippings from local New York City news sources pertaining to Berman's political platforms, such as air pollution, political ethics, and rent and housing issues. Bills introduced by New York State Senator MacNeil Mitchell and background materials about Mitchell, whom Berman defeated in the 1964 State Senate election, are abundant in Berman's research files.
Series 2, Post-Senatorial Papers, contains materials from Berman's time as the Commissioner of the New York City Rent and Housing Department and includes pamphlets, bound reports, photographs, correspondence, and drafts and final publications of articles written by Berman. There are a few items from Berman's career as a New York City Criminal Court Judge, but no materials pertaining to Berman's service on the New York State Supreme Court.
Separated Materials
Archivists transfered Joint Legislative Committee to Study Revision of Corporation Laws, Seventh Interim Report to 1963 Session of New York State Legislature to the book division of Special Collections. The catalog record for the monograph is now included in the University Library Catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Senatorial Papers, 1962-1965, Undated
Series 2 - Post-Senatorial Papers, 1963-1975, Undated
Both Series 1 and 2 are arranged alphabetically.
Politics and Politicians; Air--Pollution; Politicians--New York (State); Rent control--New York (State); Political campaigns--New York (State)--New York.; Criminal courts--New York (State)--New York.; Political ethics--United States.; New York (State)--Politics and government.; New York (N.Y.); Bills (legislative records); Clippings; Correspondence; Files by subject; Legislative Records; Photographs; Drafts (versions of documents); Official reports; Fliers (printed matters); Press Releases; Political posters; Berman, Frederic S.; Mitchell, MacNeil; New York (State). Legislature. Senate; New York (State). Criminal Court (Kings County, N.Y.); New York (City). Housing and Development Administration.
- Senatorial Papers, 1962-1965; Undated; 1; 1.75 cu. ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1, Senatorial Papers, consists of subject files collected by Frederic Berman during his campaign for and term as a New York State Senator. The folders in this series are arranged alphabetically, according to the subjects assigned by Berman.
  - 1st, 8th and 9th Assembly Districts, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 1)
  - 1964 Session-General (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 2)
  - 1965 State Legislature (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 3)
  - Advertising-Media, 1963-1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 4)
  - Air Pollution, 1963-1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 5)
  - Air Pollution-Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 6)
  - Air Pollution-Reports, 1964-1965; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 7)
  - Air Pollution-Research, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 8)
  - Article Notes and Press Releases, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 9)
  - Berman Campaign Literature, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 10)
  - Berman, F.S., 1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 11)
  - Cabinet, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 12)
  - Cabinet Memos, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 13)
  - Campaign Fliers, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 14)
  - Campaign Posters, 1964; Undated (Flat-file 1)
  - Cappellini Campaign, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 15)
  - Captain's Party, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 16)
  - Cards, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 17)
  - Cards-Control, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 18)
  - Citizen's Union, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 19)
  - Citizen's Union, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 20)
  - Clubs, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 21)
  - Columbia College Citizenship Council, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 23)
  - Correspondence-Citizen's Union, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 24)
  - Correspondence-Democratic National Committee, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 25)
  - Correspondence-General, 1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 26)
  - Crime, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 27)
  - Democratic Campaign Literature, 1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 28)
  - Democratic Clubs, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 29)
  - Democratic Program, 1965; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 30)
  - Entertainment Committee, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 31)
  - Envelopes-Control, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 32)
  - Ethics Issue-General, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 33)
  - Ethics-Senator Mitchell, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 34)
  - Finance, 1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 35)
  - Finance Committee Memos, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 36)
  - Fire Island Punch Party, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 37)
  - Frederic S. Berman-Bills, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 38)
  - French Campaign, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 39)
  - Goldwater, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 40)
  - Graphics, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 41)
  - Green Petition Signatures, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 42)
  - Harriman Art Tour, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 43)
  - Headquarters, 1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 44)
  - Heimann Campaign, 1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 45)
  - Highways, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 46)
  - Housing, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 47)
  - Javits-Clippings, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 48)
  - Javits-Literature, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 49)
  - Javits-Petitions, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 50)
  - Letters 1, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 51)
  - Letters 2, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 52)
  - Letters-Drafts, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 53)
  - Letters to the Editor, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 54)
  - Letters-Misc, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 55)
  - Lexington Democratic Clubs, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 56)
  - Liberal Party, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 57)
  - Literature-Costs, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 58)
  - Literature-Ideas, Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 59)
  - Literature-Other, Demo, 1962; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 60)
  - Literature-Republican, 1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 61)
  - Liquor Issue, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 62)
  - Local Newspapers, 1964-1965 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 1)
  - MacNeil Mitchell, 1962 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 2)
  - MacNeil Mitchell Research Committee, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 3)
  - Memos, 1965 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 4)
  - Mitchell Senate Bills, 1962 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 5-7)
  - Mitchell Senate Bills, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 8-9)
  - Newsclippings, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 10)
  - New York Law Journal, 1963 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 11)
  - Official Opening, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 12)
  - Opinion-Public, 1964; Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 13)
  - Parties, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 14)
  - Parties Ideas, Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 15)
  - Photos, 1964-1965; Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 16)
  - Polling Places, Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 17)
  - Post Office, Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 18)
  - Press Materials, 1964; Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 19)
  - Press Releases, 1964; Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 20)
  - Press Releases and Letters to the Editor, 1965 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 21)
  - Publicity, 1964; Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 22)
  - Radio, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 23)
  - Radio and Television, 1965 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 24)
  - Receiving Tickets, Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 25)
  - Redistricting, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 26)
  - Research Commission, 1964; Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 27)
  - Robert Kennedy Campaign, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 28)
  - Roll Calls-Senate, 1965; Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 29)
  - Sample letters, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 30)
  - Schools, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 31)
  - Senate Campaign, 1964; Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 32)
  - Speech dates, 1964; Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 33)
  - Spirit Masters, Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 34)
  - Student's Committee, Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 35)
  - Supplies, Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 36)
  - Talks, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 37)
  - Telegrams, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 38)
  - Telemarketing, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 39)
  - Theaters, Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 40)
  - Unknown Petition Signatures, Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 41)
  - Volunteers, Undated (Box 2 (1-Senatorial Papers), Folder 42)
- Post-Senatorial Papers, 1963-1975; Undated; 2; .25 cu. ft.
  Series 2, Post-Senatorial Papers, consists of subject files that pertain to Berman's career as the Commissioner of the New York City Rent and Housing Department. The folders in this series are also arranged alphabetically according to subjects assigned to the folders by Berman. This series also features photographs and bound reports.
  - NYC Criminal Court Decisions and Newsclippings, 1973-1975; Undated (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 43)
  - NYC Criminal Court Photos, 1973; 1975 (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 44)
  - Rent and Housing Commissioner Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 45)
  - Rent and Housing Commissioner Photos, 1966-1968 (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 46)
  - Rent Control, 1967-1968 (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 47)
  - Rent Control Publications, 1963; 1970; Undated (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 48)
  - Rent Control Reports, 1967-1968 (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 49)
  - Report to the Mayor on an Investigation into Rental Increases in the Non-Controlled Housing Market, 1969 (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 50)
  - Report:People, Housing and Rent Control in New York City, 1964 (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 51)
  - Report:The Private Rental Housing Market in New York City 1965, 1966 (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 52)
  - Report:Rent Control in New York City, 1967 (Box 2 (2-Post-Senatorial Papers), Folder 53)